<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certeyne preceptes, gathered by Hulrichus Zuinglius, declaring how the ingenious youth ought to be instructed and brought vnto Christ. Translated out of latin into Inglish by master Richard Argentyne Doctour in Physyck</title>
            <title>Quo pacto ingenui formandi sint praeceptiones pauculae. English</title>
            <author>Zwingli, Ulrich, 1484-1531.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841578</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841578</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6171</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15875)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6171)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 375:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certeyne preceptes, gathered by Hulrichus Zuinglius, declaring how the ingenious youth ought to be instructed and brought vnto Christ. Translated out of latin into Inglish by master Richard Argentyne Doctour in Physyck</title>
                  <title>Quo pacto ingenui formandi sint praeceptiones pauculae. English</title>
                  <author>Zwingli, Ulrich, 1484-1531.</author>
                  <author>Argentine, Richard, d. 1568.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Anthony Scoloker. dwellyng in. S. Nycholas paryshe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Ippeswich :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1548.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Richard Argentine, of: Zwingli, Ulrich.  Quo pacto ingenui formandi sint praeceptiones pauculae.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-c (C7 blank, -C8, also blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Education --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Moral education --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6171:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6171:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Certeyne Preceptes / gathered by Hul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richus Zuinglius / declaring howe the Ingenious youth ought to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed and brought vnto Chriſt.</p>
            <p>¶Tranſlated oute of latin into Inglyſh by Maſter Richarde Argentyne Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour in Phyſyck.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRINTED</hi> at Ippeſwich by Anthony Scoloker. Dwellyng in. S. Nycholas Parryſhe. Anno. 1548.</p>
            <p>¶Cum Priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6171:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6171:2"/>
            <head>Vnto the ryght worſhypfull Maſter Edwarde Grymeſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Richarde Argentyne / wyſſheth peace and health in Ieſu Chriſte.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as moch as Ieſu chriſt vnto whome the children were offred / Math. xix. to thintent he ſhulde laye hys handes vppon them and praye / with a fauourable countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce receauing the ſame / declared that he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to be a ſauiour alſo of ſoche / becauſe the very infauntes (as well as other of greater age) through the ſinne of Adam / had nede of the grace of God / and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me being receaued of Chriſt / are made the Cytezens of the kingdome of heauen. theſe of iuſte cauſe / are mooſt worthye prayſe / that ſhewe the very nere and next waye / howe ſuche maye be trayned vnto Chriſte / that as yet haue not the parfect vſe of reaſon / wherby fayth maye the more ſurely be graffed in them / withoute the whych it is impoſſyble to pleaſe God. For like as the ſhipma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that apointeth his iorney into forraine cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treis / though his
<pb facs="tcp:6171:3"/> ſhyp be neuer ſo well tackled / or neuer ſo good of ſayle / being without his compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe / wherby (in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtuous and darke ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes / and in the longe and obſcure nygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / he maye knowe vppon what coaſte to decline) thinketh him ſelf naked / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo the yonge a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d tender age / albeit it be neuer ſo well natured and indued with godly graces / yet of it ſelfe it is but naked / being without a guide declaring the right waie / and of nature more prone to vice than to vertue. Where therfore God hath geuen vnto you a Childe of great towardnes / furniſſhed alſo with the giftes of nature as moche as maie be. Vnto whome (for your ſake) I am bounde to owe my ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in all that I am able to do. I haue tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated this litle boke / amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt other for the ſame moſt neceſſary. That by him / the reſt of the youth that cuſtomably is very groſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly brought vp / maye the better be brought to the knowledge of god / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his holy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be trayned in vertue / to the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of their pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to their owne great commodite. Fare you well. From Ippeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich this xxviij of Ianuary. An. 1548.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6171:3"/>
            <head>Vnto Gerolde Meier a very good youngman / Huldrichus Zuinglius wiſſheth grace and peace from God and our lord Ieſus Chryſte.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN of late as thou diddeſt returne from the baynes / e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man receaued the with glad harte / (my mooſt dere yonge frende Gerolde) and dyuers willed to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure the with giftes. I thought I ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be vtterly voide of al ciuilite if I ſhuld not preſent the wyth ſome manner of gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſpecially ſeyng this cuſtume to vſe to honour thoſe that baine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues is co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monely vſed amongeſt frendes / amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt whome / for two cauſes I accounte the. The one is / becauſe thou doeſt fortunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly employ thy dyligence to learning / and the other / becauſe thou art in wages <abbr>vnd</abbr> the ſtandard of my frende Glareane. And when I ſought longe with my ſelfe / what thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g might be mooſte acceptable vnto the / at length / I found that it muſt be / eyther holy or learned / or both / that ſhulde ſerue vnto thy pleaſure. For lyke as of nature
<pb facs="tcp:6171:4"/> thou appereſt to be borne vnto godlines and vertue / ſo euen nowe of thyne owne accorde thou doeſt ſhewe forth the frutes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rbanite and elegantie the which truly are ſomewhat ripe before tyme / and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are they the more pleſaunt. Wherfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re albeit that ſearching ouer with dylyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce all my learned ſtuffe / when by no waye I coulde parforme the thinge / it remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / that I ſhuld buy your fauoure / with certeyne Godly thinges / apparteining as well to the health of the body as of the ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducing vnto vertue. Where ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in times paſt / I had / vppon counſell taken with my ſelfe / begonne to make a booke howe the ingenious youth ought to be inſtructed / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d diuers diſturbau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes had delaied my purpoſe (as the caſe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtate is of thinges preſent nowe a dayes) yet as I thought of the forenamed gifte / laying watche carefully to choſe a thinge conuenient / the memory of my olde taken cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell came into my minde. Ande albeit that I ſee the mooſt parte of men to be carefull / howe they maye dedicate their labour being finiſſhed / vnto ſome worthie
<pb facs="tcp:6171:4"/> patrone / to me it fortuned contrarie / for he is preſent a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d redie / vnto whome the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ought to be dedicate. But I lacke leaſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re and thoſe ix yeres vntill the which time this worke ought to be ſuppreſſed. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore betwixt theſe two incomodities / that vtterly ſome thinge muſt be ſent vnto the / and that my buſynes doth not permitte the ſame to be done worthelie / I haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de howe preſently / it maie be ſatiſfied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs both / I my ſelfe haue ſtolen ſo moch tyme / that without great aduyſement I haue gathered to gether a fewe preceptes. And truly / generally they ought to be fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we / but well beſtowed / leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o moch copie ſhuld make lothſomenes. For ſo almooſt it commeth to paſſe / that thinges that are with a ſparing hand drawen forth are ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken in with the more gredy ſtomake. The which thynges thou ſhalt not eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me after the place from whence they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue their fyrſt originall / but according vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the meaning and intent of him from whence they procede. For Godly thinges / we maye without diſſimulation promis / if in oure ſelues we are not voide of grace / 
<pb facs="tcp:6171:5"/> But to promiſe learned thinges / it is a ſhame / although thou thy ſelfe be neuer ſo well learned. The fyrſt preceptes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne in them / howe the tender and yonge minde of an Ingenious ſtrippling is to be adorned / in thoſe thinges that appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne vnto God. The ſeconde / howe in thoſe thynges that apparteine vnto hym ſelfe. The thirde / howe in thoſe thinges that apparteine vnto other. And here / it is not oure purpoſe to beginne from the ſwadlingbanddes / nor yet from the firſt rudimentes / but from that age the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che beginneth to haue the vſe of diſcretion and witte / and beginneth to ſwimme (as the prouerbe ſaith) without a barke / in the which age euen nowe thou thy ſelfe arte. Theſe (as I truſt) thou wilt reade dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently / and wilt tranſforme thy ſelfe into them / that vnto other alſo / thou maieſt exhibyt a liuely example and token of the ſame. The which Chriſt the mightie lorde graunt vnto the. So be it. At Straeſburch the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendes of Auguſte 15. 32.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="aphorisms">
            <pb facs="tcp:6171:5"/>
            <head>The Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmes (the whyche are called brefe ſentences partetly declaring the abſolute meaning of the thing) of the fyrſt Preceptes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore all thinges / ſeing it lyeth not in the power of man to drawe the harte of any one vnto the faith of one god although any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhulde paſſe in perſuading Pericies / but it lyeth only in god the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father / who doth drawe vs vnto him. And yet nothwythſtandyng / ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto the ſaying of the Apoſtle / faith is by hearing (ſo that the hearing be the worde of God) not truly that the prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching of the worde is of ſo great force / ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the ſpirite working in vs / g ue vs ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſement vnto the ſame. And therfore faith muſt be inſtilled with mooſt pure wordes / and mooſt vſed to procede from the mouth of God / And prayers ioyned
<pb facs="tcp:6171:6"/> vnto the ſame muſt be made vnto hym / who onely doth make the faithfull / that whome we teache with worde / he maie il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate the ſame with his ſpirit.</p>
            <p>And perchaunce it ſhall not be alienate from the purpoſe of Chriſte / if we bring the ſame into the knowledge of God / yea / by thinges that are viſible. As if we call before oure eyes / the ingent of the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall worlde / declari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or ſhewing with our finger / that all thinges are ſubiect vnto al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teration / but it is neceſſary that he be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable / and not moued / the which hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs / (ſeing they be ſo diuerſe) in ſo firme ande marvailous a concorde. Ande againe it ought not to be ſuſpected that he that hath diſpoſed al thinges with ſo great a prouidence / will he after neglect his owne handy worke / for as moch as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt mortall men / it is imputed as a vice or blame / if any man be not dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or carefull in the thing that apparteineth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to his houſe.</p>
            <p>Of this / the ſame our dearli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſhall lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the pouidence of God / who careth for all thinges / diſpoſeth all thinges and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth
<pb facs="tcp:6171:6"/> all thinges. For of the two ſparro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes that are bought for a farthi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne falleth not vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grounde vnto vs / without his counſell. Who alſo hath no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the heares of oure heades / nothinge vtterly is left out of this care. Wherby it is manifeſt that the ſame doth determine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not onely of thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges wherof the ſoule hath nede / but alſo the body / ſeing we ſee the Rookes ſo liberally to be entre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eined by the ſame / ande the lilies alſo ſo gally to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ladde.</p>
            <p>Hitherto / the minde being rightly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſhed or inſtructed of the prouidence of god / it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be that it may be at any time carefull / or oute of ordre ſtryken with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetuouſnes. The whiche affect if in our tendre age we cut from vs than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e we delyuered the minde from a great dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and hurtefull plage.</p>
            <p>He ſhall knowe truly that God is not onely a lorde / but alſo a father of all thoſe that beleue in him / that is / of thoſe that truſt in him and that he deſyreth that we ſhall come with as moch haſte vnto hym / to craue for helpe / as vnto the parent or
<pb facs="tcp:6171:7"/> father that hath begotten vs / ande with his propre wordes hath promiſed helpe / becauſe certeynly he loueth to be prayed.</p>
            <p>Wherfore if the ſycknes eyther of min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de or of body do vexe or greue the / the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medye muſt be obteyned from him / if thy ennemy do trouble the / if envie do oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe the / thou muſt runne vnto hym. If we covet wiſdome or learni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g we muſt wowe him for them / yea bothe wife and children are alſo to be deſired at his hand.</p>
            <p>If the increaſe of goodes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d honoures come a litle to plentyfully vnto vs / we muſt deſyre of hym / that he wyll not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our mynd to be made to tendre wyth them or effemyna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e / ande ſo to be brought oute of the right waye.</p>
            <p>What nede many wordes? generally / he ſhall knowe that all thinges are to be aſked of him and he ſhall thinke it a wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / to aſke any thinge of him / that ſhall not be condecent for him to parforme / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d fynal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſhalbe a ſhamed eyther to couet or to haue any thyng the which by hym is not laufull / and he ſhall onely get and laye vp in treaſure thoſe thinges that maketh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:6171:7"/> truly happie.</p>
            <p>He ſhall vnderſtand the miſtery of the Goſpell this waies / he ſhall knowe befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re all other thinges the ſtate of the fyrſt manne / that is to ſaye / howe he through death is deade againe / howe after that he had tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſed the precept of God / he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by his tranſgreſſe all his poſterite. For the dead can not beget the lyuyſh / nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue we euer ſene a blacke morian borne amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt Ingliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherby / this our frende ſhall know alſo his diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>Alſo by this he doth knowe / if he do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand howe we do all thinges by the motions of our affectes / howe God truly is farre of from them. Wherby it follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vndoubtedly / that we alſo ſhulde be mooſt clere without all affectes if we ſhal deſire to dwell with God. For like as eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry innocent / hath nothing to do with tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe that are mooſt geuen vnto myſchefe / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary the wicked can not abide the iuſt. For as thoſe that are of the nature of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro do bidde and commaund other like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Seneca to be handeled / euen ſo of the contrarie / the ſame tumbe doth hyde or co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:6171:8"/> the Emyans with the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pians / ſo none other ſhall inhabit with God / than he that is wythout ſpot ande holy / as God hym ſelf is holy / ande indued with the purenes of harte. For bleſſed are the pure in harte becauſe they ſhall ſee God. But howe ſhall we get ſo great an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency / the which are nedged round<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> abou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te with mooſt impure affectes? we being here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> betwixt the hammer and the ſtithe for ſo moch as God doth require ſo great an innocencie / we beyng corrupted / can of our ſelues do nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g but vice / whether we will or not we are compelled to yelde vnto God and to permit all thinges vnto his grace. Here ſpringeth the light of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>When we are incloſed wyth theſe ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yghtes / Chriſt doth take vs oute / the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath deliuered vs farre better / than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great God of the Gentyles that was thought to preſerue them / aboue all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / erecting the conſcience nere vnto deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration / ande ſone after when by mooſt aſſured hope he hath ioyned the ſame vnto hym / makyng it fortunate. For ſeyng he
<pb facs="tcp:6171:8"/> is moſt clere without all blotte of all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted affectes conceiued truly of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighooſt / and borne of a pure virgin. Firſt to deliuer vs he did ſett forth this his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency for vs. For truly he ſuffered oure labours and paynes / ande afterwarde he maketh thoſe which vndoubtedly beleue thys / bleſſed.</p>
            <p>For he that ſhall beleue this lyberall pardon / graunted of God by Chriſt / vnto the miſerable kinde of mortall ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / he ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſaued / ande beyng made the coheyre of Chriſt / he ſhalbe in ioye with the father e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtinge. For he wyll that where hym ſelfe is / there alſo his miniſter ſhalbe</p>
            <p>The innocency of Chriſt that was put in daunger for thoſe that were gylte / yea for the dampned / hath abſolued vs / and hath made vs worthy vnto God for this cauſe ſpecially / becauſe he was able to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyll the maner and meaſure of the dyuine iuſtice. For he was mooſt clere without all corrupted affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And where as he is ſoche and ſo great of him ſelf / that is to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye God / yet was he made oures. Wherof it followeth / that his iuſtice (the whych
<pb facs="tcp:6171:9"/> onely thinge we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acke) was alſo made ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. For he was made vnto vs from god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wiſdome / iuſtice / holines and redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Nowe / by him we haue an entraunce vnto God. For he is oures the pledge of the grace of God / our Aduocate / oure ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere oure head / interceſſour ande media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour. He is our whole truſt and affiaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce both fyrſt and laſt.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that hetherto vnderſtand the miſtery of the Goſpell a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d truſt vppon the ſame / are borne of God for the capacite of mannes weakenes can not attaine vnto ſo profounde a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell of the grace of god.</p>
            <p>Out of this it commeth / that thoſe that are borne a newe of the Goſpell / can not ſynne. For euery ſoch one as is borne of God doth not ſynne. But he that bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the Goſpell / is borne of God / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they do not ſynne that are borne ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of the Goſpell. That is to ſaie / the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes are not impu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed vnto them vnto da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion and death becauſe Chryſt hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demed them with the price of his death. For albeyt that we (as longe as we are in this body trauaylyng as it were in pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb facs="tcp:6171:9"/> from God) cannot be wythout af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo by that means alſo / not wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout ſynne. Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chryſt notwythſtandi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g becauſe he is ours / doth ſupply or amend all this our impote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cye or weakenes. For ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g he is god aeternal a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a ſpirite / he is mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re precyous to redeme the ſines of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / than they them ſelues are able to deſerue.</p>
            <p>For Ood trulye as he is a ſubſtanciall forme or power that turneth and moueth all thynges in it ſelfe / not beynge moued / wyll not ſuffer hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo / whoſe hart he hath drawen vnto him / to be ſlouthful or ydle. The which ſentence truly is not knowen by probacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s but by vſe. For onelye thoſe that are faythfull haue in experience how Chryſte geueth no ydlenes at all vnto hys ſervauntes / and wyth howe glad a ſpirite and wyth howe moche ioye they travayle and are exerciſed in thys buſynes.</p>
            <p>Wherfore / who ſo ever vnderſtandeth the miſterie of the Goſpel / he goeth about to liue wel. Wherfore that muſt be taught as moche as maye be very purely a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently.</p>
            <p>And thys alſo muſt as the tyme requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:6171:10"/> he taught / by what kynde of meanes ſpeciallye we maye deſerue the fauoure of God / by thoſe things certeynly / whych he him ſelfe vſeth alwayes towardes vs / by iuſtice / fayth and mercy. For ſeing God is a ſpirite / he can no otherwyſe be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped rightly with any other ſacrifice / than wyth the ſpirituall ſacrifice of an humble mynd. Wherfore let our derling or you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man bende his intente to this ende / howe with all maturite he maye be a good man; howe he maye be innocent / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as nere ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto God as maye be.</p>
            <p>He doth good vnto all menne / he doth hurte no man / except a man fyrſt hurte hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe. So he that doth ſtudie to do good vnto all men / and to be euery thinge vnto all men / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doth abſtaine vtterly his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de from all iniurie / he is mooſt like vnto God. Theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges are harde / if thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue an eye vnto oure owne ſtrength / but vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to him that beleueth / all thinges are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="aphorisms">
            <head>The Aphoriſmes of the ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de preceptes.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:6171:10"/>
            <p>After that the minde / whyche muſt be appointed vnto ſubſtanciall vertue / ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be rightly inſtructed by faith / the next thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge is / that he decke ande furniſh him ſelfe all wholy within purely. For if with hym ſelfe all thinges be in a right ordre / than ſhall he very ſone gyue good counſell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other.</p>
            <p>And he can not more lightly ſett his mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in due order / than if he haue in hand / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d labour both night ande daye in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of God. The whiche thinge he ſhall do very well / if he vnderſtande the hebrue and greke tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gues rightly / becauſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the one of them / the olde Teſtament / and without the other / the newe can not without difficulte purely be knowen.</p>
            <p>And for as moch as we haue taken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs to teache thoſe / that haue nowe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ouer the trauaile of their firſt rudime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. And the Latin tongue being had in vſe amongeſt all men / yet do we not think it mete vtterly to leaue it. For albeit that it do conduce leſſe vnto the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of holy ſcriptures / then eyther the Greke or Hebrue tongue / yet for the
<pb facs="tcp:6171:11"/> reſt vſe of our life it proficeth very mothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſometimes it cometh to paſſe / that we haue to do in the buſynes of Chriſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt thoſe that are onely latyn men. But to abuſe the tongues for againe / that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ought to be farre of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For truly the tongues are the gifte of the ſpyryte of God.</p>
            <p>The next vnto this / vnto whome we ſhall giue our diligence / ſhalbe the Greke tongue / becauſe of the newe Teſtaments as it is ſaide (for ſpeaking the thinge / that I thinke offending no man wyllingly) The doctryne of Chriſte euen from the beginning (not as the thinge required) ſo rightly to haue bene handled of the latin men / as of the grekes. Wherfore this our dearling muſt be ſent vnto the fyrſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes.</p>
            <p>Albeit this in them both is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / that the ſame haue his harte ſtrongly walled aboute with faith ande innocency. For there are many thinges that wolde be learned not withoute daunger / wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / the deſyre of Empire a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to liue in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of battaill / intertaine froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:6171:11"/>
/ vaine Philoſophy a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſuche like thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. All the which thinges / a minde being moniſſhed of them before / may paſſe ouer not touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them / like vnto Vliſſes. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the fyrſt voice or hearing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / he hath thus moniſſhed him ſelfe / Theſe thinges thou heareſt to beware and not to be enta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with them / or to take them. We giue the laſt place to the hebrue tongue for this cauſe ſpecially / becauſe as we haue ſaid a litle before / the latin tongue is growen in knowledge amongeſt all men. And the Greke to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue ſhall mooſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniently fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the ſame or elles wolde we of iuſt right haue geuen the firſt place vnto the hebrue tongue / becauſe without the phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of that tongue / yea in the greke tongue he ſhall ſweate who ſoeuer will vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or ſearche out the right ſence of the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. But to ſpeake of the vtilité of the ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues to the full / it aparteyneth not to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Who ſoeuer commeth with an humble and thurſty minde / with theſe armours / he maye breake into this heauenly wiſdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vnto whome no wiſdome of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye
<pb facs="tcp:6171:12"/> be compared / nor yet of right matched.</p>
            <p>Vnto the which / when he hath broken in / he ſhall finde all kindes of formes to liue well / that is to witte Chriſt him ſelfe the mooſt abſolute exemple of all vertue / whome / when by worde and dede he ſhall aſſuredly or plainly knowe / he ſhal ſo em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace / that in euery acte or counſell / he ſhal endeuour to expreſſe ſome parte of his vertues / as moch as by right the tenuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>té or weakenes of man wyll ſuffre to be done.</p>
            <p>He ſhal learne of him as the oportunité of time ſhall require both to ſpeake and to holde his peace. It ſhalbe a ſhame for him to tymely to ſpeake of thoſe thinges why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che require none but ſoche as are come to a parfectripenes / becauſe he may ſee Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte to haue layde vp this ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly at the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth in the thurtieth yere of his age. Albeit that he did giue ſome experiment of him ſelfe vnto the doctours of the lawe alſo when he was twelue yeares olde. By the whych exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple we are not ſo moch taught to come forth in tyme / as we are to ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure euen from our tender age thynges
<pb facs="tcp:6171:12"/> that are great / but worthy vnto God.</p>
            <p>For like as the greateſt ornament or commendacion vnto a woman through oute all her life is ſcylence. So nothing doth make a yongman more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtudy of ſcile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eine time / vntyll the mynde and the tonge as well a parte / as amongeſt them ſelues can agre well. And we require not here the Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goricall ſcylence / but we do onely ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe the deſyre to ſpeake. Ande except the yongman ſhall ſpeake tymely / we do for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byd him to ſpeake at all.</p>
            <p>Whyles he ſtudieth the preceptes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence / beyng vnder hys maſters / he ſhall not deforme or bring it oute of faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyon / becauſe he wyll followe theyr ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emple if it haue any faute. Ande let no man thinke this precept to be of a lyght force. For it is to be learned by the olde auncient hiſtories / that certayne Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours or learners haue not onely follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed by imitations the vices or fautes of theyr teachers tongue / but alſo of theyr bodyes.</p>
            <p>The fautes of the to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue / maye be ſone
<pb facs="tcp:6171:13"/> knowe vnto euery body. For truly the for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of an Oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſydes the worckman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of it / is corrupted / if the ſame be ſpoken to faſt or to ſlowly. If the acce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing of it / be to baſe or fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / or to vehement / as if in euery cauſe / and in euery kinde of thinge there be but one forme of countenannce / ande one maner of geſture / or faming as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do call it / that is done with inſolencie.</p>
            <p>It is obſerued / that Elepha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are alone / are carefull ande ſtudious to call to minde thoſe thinges / for the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che they haue bene beaten. So a yongma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall often ſtudy with him ſelfe / howe to compoſe his tonge or countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / howe to vſe his handes / like vnto one that may where nede ſhall require / with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient ſhame faſtnes be as a loadeſman / ſhewi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thinges vnto other / ande to procede ande not to rowe backe againe. And all theſe thinges he ſhal ſo moderate / that they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye ſerue the truth / and not to ſerue in flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie vnto other. For the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicions or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſome that are like vnto the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions of an harlot howe can they be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured
<pb facs="tcp:6171:13"/> or ſuffred of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> harte? Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore by this exerciſe that we do here requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / we do inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d none other thing / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that euery man maye learne with him ſelfe / to rule the exteriour vices / the which are the mooſt certeine tokens of a corrupte min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Wherfore it is fyrſt neceſſarie that the minde of it ſelfe be parfect / the which / if it ſo be / ſhall ſone moderate the raging tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt of the exteriour membres / that we do not frowne to moche / or alter our mouth or contenaunce / or ſhake our heade / or caſt abroade our handes / but that we tempre all theſe thinges / with a certeine modeſté / not affected / but plaine and ful of ſymply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cité. Theſe thinges are of the Oration or ſpeakyng / and of ſcilence.</p>
            <p>He ſhall flye the ſaturité or fulnes of wine / as moch as he wolde homlocke. Forlike as it doth driue this tender bodie or yonge Carcas (the which of his owne nature is prone vnto vehemency) vnto madnes / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo doth it (without doubte) corrupt our olde age / that as yet tarieth for vs / euen in the firſt ſpringing of vs. Wherby it commeth to paſſe / that when
<pb facs="tcp:6171:14"/> by chaunce we come vnto it / we finde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmité and ſicknes / and no reſt. For it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no otherwiſe be / but thoſe that haue to bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſily vſed to waſſhe them ſelues with wine / but that they muſt fall into ſome greuous and daungerous ſickenes / as the fallinge ſickenes / a palſie / a dropſie / the leprie / ande ſoch other. Wherfore couet not to ſone to be an olde man / if thou wilt be an olde ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> longe.</p>
            <p>Let the reſt of his diet be ſoch thinges as may be ſone gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For what doth it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to a yong ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (whoſe ſtomake by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d redy to parfect diſgeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to deſire to fede vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> partrig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s thruſſhes deintie byrdes / Capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / of Roobuckes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſoch other deintie diſſhes? Let him laie vp thoſe in ſtore / tyll age come vppon hym / when his tethe ſhalbe dull or blunte / ande the palate of his mouth tendre or worne / and his throte / with longe continuaunce of time / growen to a certeine hardnes / ande his Stomake not beinge q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ycke or able to digeſte / ande his bodye half dead. For what hope ſhalbe to nouriſh the olde
<pb facs="tcp:6171:14"/> age yf the wanton youth / by intemperate dyet / hath made ſoch thynges lothſome / whiche the olde age ſhuld mooſt deſyre?</p>
            <p>Hunger in the meane tyme / is onely to be conuinced or ouercome / ande not to be put awaye. For men ſaye that Galen ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued hundreth and twenty yeres / becauſe he neuer departed full from the table. And I do not here require / that thou ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt puniſh thy ſelf with famyn / but that thou ſhuldeſt not ſerue the inſatiable vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racité or rauening / more than the vſe of the lyfe doth requyre. For I am not ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt but that I knowe / that a man maye offend in both partes. If that in rauenyng we make our ſelues lyke vnto wolues / or by famine / make our ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proffytable or not able to do any good.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe nothing to be more folyſh / than to covet to be taken as a gentelman / becauſe of ryche and gaye apparell. For by that meanes / the Byſſhoppes Mules maye chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge nobilitié / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be moch bruted.
<pb facs="tcp:6171:15"/> For they / for as moch as they be ſtronges are able to cary more gold and ſyluer / and more pretious ſtones / than euer any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo coulde. And who can not be aſhamed of his proude apparell / that heareth the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God / borne of a vyrgyne / to ligh crying in an oxe ſtalle? being wrapped aboute o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely with ſo many bandes / as the virgin / not being prepared to her deliuerie / bare wyth her?</p>
            <p>Thoſe that daily do fynde oute ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ande newe ſhapes of garmentes / do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare / a mooſt certaine token of an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunt (or if that be to moche) of an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminate or tender minde. Thoſe are not of Chriſte / for they ſuffer the poore in the meane whyle to periſh wyth colde ande hunger. Wherfore a man muſt as moche abſtaine from the ſuperfluité of garmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes or apparell / as of any other kynde of evell.</p>
            <p>While the yongman beginneth to be in loue / he muſt exhibit ſome beginninge of exerciſe of his minde. And while other do trie their armes / where a tumulte is / with ſtrength and armours / this our dearling
<pb facs="tcp:6171:15"/> ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert all his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to this purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe / that he maye defend him ſelfe from the madnes of loue. And when he ſhall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue vtterly that he muſt loue in dede / to beware that he doate not / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to choſe ſoche a one to his loue / whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicions he tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth to be able to endure in perpetuall ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trymonie / and ſo vndefyledly or chaſtly to kepe their congreſſe or meting to gether / vntill the time of Mariage / that beſydes her / amongeſt all the numbre or multitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of women a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d virgines he knowe none.</p>
            <p>For what purpoſe or nede / doth it ſerue in this caſe to forbidde the deſire of money and glory / when euen amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles / this kynde of miſchefe / is euell ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of? And this our dearling ought not to be taken hereafter as a Chriſtian / yf he ſhall become ſeruaunt vnto that / the whiche hath troden vnder foote / not one or two / but hath ſubuerted the mooſt floryſſhyng kyngdomes / hath deſtroyed the myghtye ſtronge Cities / and what ſoeuer publyke weale it hath inuaded / it hath vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done the ſame. This when it hath in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſyon the pryncypall towre of mannes
<pb facs="tcp:6171:16"/> mynde or ſoule / it permytteth nothyng to be well done / ande is the mooſt hurtefull plage of all the woorlde / but / alas / it is of a great power / which we ſhall kyll or deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troye by Chryſt alone / if we ſhalbe the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygent or buſy followers of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For what other thynge dyd he here elles / than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy thys evell?</p>
            <p>We thynke the Mathematicall diſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plines / vnto the which alſo / men do num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre Muſike / not lyghtly to be touched / al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit not dwellyng longe in them. For lyke as they beyng knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are very moche fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefull or neceſſarye / ande beyng not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded / are no ſmall impediment / euen ſo if a man ſhall ſpend all his time in them / eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his old age / he ſhall haue none other fru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te by it / then thoſe haue / whiche / becauſe they wyll not be ydle / walkinge vp ande downe / chaunge nowe ande than theyr place.</p>
            <p>The exercyſe of contencyon or of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours / we do not ſo moche condempne / as wyllyng notwithſtanding to pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce otherwiſe in this matter / yf we did not
<pb facs="tcp:6171:16"/> ſee certeyne great ryche men conſtauntly to abhorre from that labour / which doth helpe the commone lyfe. Yet ſhall it be the parte of a chriſtian man vtterly to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne from weapons as moche as maye be laufull by the ſtate and tranquillyté of the publike weale. For GOD / who brought home Dauid as a conqurour / being rude in the handelinge of weapons / goying forthwith his ſlinge agaynſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liath / and preſerued the Iſraelites / bryng vnarmed from their preſent ennemy / will preſerue vs alſo vndoubtedlye / ande if it ſhall otherwyſe pleaſe him. He ſhall har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas ande make ſtronge oure handes / He trulie doth teach our handes vnto the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flict or fight. But if it be Vtterly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined / to put in experience / this exerciſe of weapons / let this onely be the chefe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of it / that we will defend our natiue contrey ande thoſe whome GOD com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth to be defended.</p>
            <p>I wolde therfore every man (ande chefely / not withſtandinge thoſe that are to be appointed vnto the office of the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of GOD) to thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke no otherwiſe than
<pb facs="tcp:6171:17"/> that howe they may attayne vnto the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Citie / ad in that alone / of the olde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylyans the whiche dyd accompte no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to be in the nombre of theyr Cytezens, that knewe no crafte howe to gett his liuyng. For by that meanes / it ſhuld come to paſſe that ydlenes (the cauſe or mainteyner of al diſſolute behaueour) or wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes / ſhuld be banniſhed / and our bodies ſhuld moch longer be preſerued in health ſhuld lyve longer and br of greater ſtrength.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="aphorisms">
            <head>The Aphoryſmes of the laſte Preceptes.</head>
            <p>Fyrſt of all this ſhall the ingenious mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke with himſelfe / Chriſt hath giuen him ſelfe for vs ande is made oures and ſo is it neceſſarye that thou be geuen vnto a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>men not to thynke thy felt to be thyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> owne man but to be for other. For trulye we are not borne vnto our ſelues / but th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at we ſhuld be all thinges vnto all men.</p>
            <p>Wherfore from hys tender age he ſhall muſt vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe things alone vppon iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyce fayth and conſtauntye by the which he maye do good vnto the chryſtyan pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyke
<pb facs="tcp:6171:17"/> weale and vnto his natiue coutrey ande particulerly alſo vnto all men. For thoſe are ſpeke and feble mindes / that only do regard this thyng / howe they maye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue or come by a quiet lyuing / ande are not ſo lyke vnto God / as thoſe are / that euen with their owne perill do ſtudie how to do good vnto all men.</p>
            <p>Ande here notwithſtanding this muſt he warelye taken hede of leaſt the purpoſe that is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to the glory of God of our natiue countrey ande the proffit of all men / be not defiled or corrupted by the deuell or the loue of our ſelues / and finally that we take not the thing vnto our ſelues the whiche we will appeare to haue done; for the cauſe of other men. For why? we maye ſee many which in the firſt beginni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g go happely in the ryght trade / and wythin a lytle after / through vayne glory (whiche is the peſtilence of all godly intentes) they are driuen out of the ryght path.</p>
            <p>In the proſperite ande aduerſité of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men / he ſhall euen like behaue him ſelf as though they had for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned vnto his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne parſon. Yf good fortune ſhall come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:6171:18"/> an other / he ſhall thinke th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is hath for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuned vnto him ſelf as well a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e aduerſite. For why the ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t none pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike weale lyke vnto one houſe and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Yea one bodye in the wyth the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres are ſo glad together and do ſorrowe ande the one helpeth the other that what ſoeuer ſhal fortune to one ſhalbe thought to happen to all.</p>
            <p>After this ſort / he ſhalbe glad with the ioyfull and ſhall wipe with thoſe that do wepe / for why<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? he ſhall thinke the chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of euery man to be his owne. Adde vnto this that accordyng vnto the ſaying of Senica / the thinge maye happen vnto every man that doth fortune vnto any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. And we do not teache that theſe afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ioye ande ſorrowe muſte be ſo vſed as the comone cuſtome is. For we wyll not that we ſhall make myrth and ioie in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and deſpayr in aduerſite. But for as moche / as we are never wythout theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d other affectes / ſo if wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> wiſe we muſt tempre them / that in no caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> admitte any inconueniente / or do the thing that is not comely / Wherfore we ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>athe as moche
<pb facs="tcp:6171:18"/> of the proſperitie as other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> other wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall we be ſep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> / tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſay / we ſhal take al things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion.</p>
            <p>From theſe conuenticles or company<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es where as men mete / many together or commely ſoche as are the mariages of ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditates that are yerely kepte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidates. I make no great reſtrainte becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> chriſt in times paſt hath been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vnki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly part of maryages. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> mooſte alowe / that if the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt nedes be done be done in ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> place or ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly rather then in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> houſes / becauſe the mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude of witneſſes / doth more vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their owne propre mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. For he ſhal wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t all grace / that is not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> openly o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> comunely to do the thynge that is diſhoneſt or vncomely.</p>
            <p>From the comune conuenticles or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges together of men / he ſhall alwayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g away ſom goodnes / leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke as Socrates was accuſtomed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine returne home alwaes worke. He ſhal marke of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be haue hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe abrode
<pb facs="tcp:6171:19"/> with honeſt ſhame faſtnes / and ſhall follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we it. And of the contrarie without ſhame he ſhall refuſe it or deſpiſe it.</p>
            <p>But for as moche as thoſe that are full rype of one conſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly do this / mine adviſe is that they mete together in publyke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles as ſeldome as maye be. But if of neceſſite ſometimes madnes muſte be had in companye ſone after let vs come home agayne to our ſelves / a ſone reaſon may be pretended why we haue forſaken our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues / vnto the which / thoſe muſt be agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that do knowe that we are geuen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vnto vertuous or good ſtudyes.</p>
            <p>In things that are paynefull / our bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilles muſt be lowſed for vs to runne. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n this caſe it is accounted a noble thinge to be fyrſt and laſt. In this ſhuld we ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atch our ſinnewes forth the evell to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydered / to be ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deled to be amoued or put awaye / and counſell to be geven.</p>
            <p>And it is vſed even amongeſt the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delles / that our parentes next vnto the im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mortal God are mooſt to be left by. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore we muſt gyve place vnto them every where. Ande if at any tyme they behave
<pb facs="tcp:6171:19"/> not them ſhoes after the minde of Chryſt / the which is alſo dures / we maye not due of ſeaſon ſtryue againſt them / but what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ought to be ſayde or done / that muſt be proponed or purpoſed with al medenes the which thinge if they wyll not receave / they are rather to be forſaken than to be handeled contumelyouſly.</p>
            <p>The naturall Philoſophers do teſtifie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> / that Ire dranger commeth of a hote cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe / wherfore this yong age is mooſt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we muſt dilygently beware of it that we do not ſaye any thinge by the compulſyon therof / what ſoeuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth into the mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. When this after it is hoate in the / it ought to be ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>Sclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der / if we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not vtterly / becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of the bitternes of it / digeſt it downe / it muſt be referred vnto ſome iudge or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate. For why? to render agayne one the eke for a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other or to fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ouer againe the ſclaunder or contumely vnto him that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve it / it is no other / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be like vnto hym or ſuch one as he is whome thou doeſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alowe.</p>
            <p>Games with theyr equalles we do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6171:20"/> to ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e vp did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>och <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of / learni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ande profitable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the exerr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bodye. The games of learning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> contend with aua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tike doth reach / or vyse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tyng of places the which thing the / draught<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and pauſes of the cheſtes and theyr ſtacions alſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and heal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inges in watch do declare. For that ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> aboue all other doth teach / that noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e ought to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one raſhlye or vnaduiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dlye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And yet in the meane tyme the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> meane kept in it. For them have and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> me / which / ſetti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g their ſerious buſines a parte / haue geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to that onely. We permit onely theſe thinges to be done in / by times / or in the tymes of leaſure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other thinges. And the games of dice and cardes (as men call them) we count ande ſend them backe agayn vnto the crowes / as the Prouerbe ſaith.</p>
            <p>The body ſhalbe exerciſed with run<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> leaping / coyting with the exercyſe of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / with wraſtli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g (the which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeldo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be vſed / becauſe ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times it euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed earneſt (and with ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> paſtimes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e almooſt generally in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="tcp:6171:20"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as haue bene vſed mooſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r forefathers the Zwytſers beinge verye proffitable for dyuers chaunces. I ſee that ſwi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming is proffitable to very fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we albeit ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme it is a pleaſure to ſwi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me in the water or ryver lyke vnto a fiſh / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it hath ſerued ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times for chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces not with out proffit. He came ſwi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng out of the Capitolhouſe that ſhuld declare vnto Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millos the miſerable ſtate of Auarous Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me. Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with her owne propre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres returned agayne vnto hers.</p>
            <p>Let all the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation and talke alſo / be ſoche that may delight thoſe with who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me we do lyue.</p>
            <p>And if thou muſt nedes chyde an other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / do it with ſo good a harte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo drily / and let it be done ſo pretily a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo aduyſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / that we maye put awaye the vice ande wynne the man / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ioyne him wyth more hart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e or entyre love vnto vs.</p>
            <p>The ſtudye of trouth muſt be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ande alone that alwayes we muſte p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder ſo / both our owne talke a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the tale or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of other / 
<pb facs="tcp:6171:21"/> that no craft or rayning be mixed in it. And a good minde ought to be w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing more diſpleaſed with hym ſelf tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yf he perceaue any lye come from him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> though it be againſt his wyll. I will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaye here howe moch he ought to be a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med if he make them him ſelf or tell them when they are made of others. For euery man is commaunded to ſpeake the truth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which his neighbour. Chriſt is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the. Wherfore it becommeth a Chriſtian man to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owe and kepe moſt diligently the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in mynde or in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in all his wayes. Nothing can be aſſuredly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to hym that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> this t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wherfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if that be vai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> lying ande inconſtant all is a mooſt certaine token that the harte i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> worſſe a great deale. Adde vnto this that a lye maye be for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tyme hydden / but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for euer. Wherfore it ſhal be a very folyſh thinge / to nouriſh or comforte the domes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>all noughty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>achte in hope that it ſhal be hydden / or not knowen.</p>
            <p>Loke what I haue ſaide of the ſtudie of
<pb facs="tcp:6171:21"/> the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the ſame muſt be obſerued in all doinges / that we do nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g fainedly / that our browe or eyes diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble no other thing / than the harte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> meaneth / the whiche is the fountaine of all doinges.</p>
            <p>The going alſo that is made or forged / doth giue a ſufficient argument / what the man is the which doth go otherwiſe than his nature requireth / that is to ſaye / full of vanité / and an harlot in minde.</p>
            <p>But what nedeth many wordes? To this purpoſe all ſtudie muſt be haſted / that the yongman maye with all purenes ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke into him Chriſte / who) when he hath dronken or taſted of him) he ſhalbe a rule vnto him. He ſhal neuer fall from well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall neuer be prowde or extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / he ſhall encreaſe dailie / but he ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to him ſelf alwaies to decreaſe. He ſhall go forward / but he ſhall accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te hym ſelfe to be luſt of all men. He ſhall do good towardes all men / but he ſhall embroide nothinge. For ſo truly Chriſte hath done. Wherfore he ſhalbe abſolute that ſhal pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe onely to followe Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the thynges (mooſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t
<pb facs="tcp:6171:22"/> Gerolde) whyche we haue thought to be proffytable or to conduce to bring vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngmen / howe be it they be ſo confuſely taught that of it ther ſacketh no declaration. For why? the thinge is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſtly open vnto the eyes of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But for thy parte remembre theſe thinges of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with thy ſelfe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d loke what thou ſeeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> here written with a rude ſtyle / expreſſe it in thy maners. And ſo it ſhal come to paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges that are poured oute he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re all mooſt without any ordre / thou thy ſelfe by thy actes / ſhalte bringe them into a very goodly ordre. Ande ſhalt be of this forme of teachyng a brething hore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de lyuely example. And to ſpeake more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtauntly / it can not other wilt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> after thou ſhalt be more abſolute than we are able to expreſſe with wordes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly thou emploie / all thy indeuoure. The which thinge ſhalbe aboue meaſure prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the expelli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of Idelnes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſome wythout all ſhame / of a miſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous receaued cuſtome / are growe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſtouth / euen in the very fyrſt entrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theyr life / that they appeare to couet to
<pb facs="tcp:6171:22"/> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thinge then dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes / ande the puddles of all vices. But thou truly (as he ſaith) muſt vſe diſcretly thy ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. For ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> age glideth away with a ſwifte foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. And not ſo good followeth as the fyrſt wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. It is the parte of a Chriſtian man / not to ſpeake lordly of opinions / but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to do thynges that are hard ande great with God. Procede therfore (thou Gentle yongman) to increaſe wyth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeruauntes of nobilite / thy kynred or ſtocke thy goodly forme a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thy patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e or in heritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / the which all hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned honourably vnto the (I haue not ſayde well) I ſhulde haue ſayde to thynke onely theſe to be the ornamentes / ande to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nowe the other thinges to be the giftes of fortune. The mooſt greateſt and mightie lorde being thy guyde. Who preſerue the in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous eſtate. So be it.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:6171:23"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>Proue the ſpyrytes whether they be of God. Ihon the iiij.i. Reg xiij.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Mat vij.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6171:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
